Guide to the Gold Rush Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gold Rush Collection
1847-1882
WA MSS S-2865
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
This collection encompasses accessions of single letters and small groups of letters and other manuscripts, pertaining to the California Gold Rush, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Letters discuss voyages to the Pacific coast, including journeys through Panama; mining life in California; the inhabitants of California, including Mormons; vigilance committees in San Francisco; and the establishment of a police force in Nevada City, California. Some letters include pictorial letterheads.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded in the finding aid or on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection encompasses accessions of single letters and small groups of letters and other manuscripts, pertaining to the California Gold Rush, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Letters discuss voyages to the Pacific coast, including journeys through Panama; mining life in California; the inhabitants of California, including Mormons; vigilance committees in San Francisco; and the establishment of a police force in Nevada City, California.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by creator.
Gold mines and mining -- California; Overland journeys to the Pacific; Miners -- California; Frontier and pioneer life -- California; Voyages to the Pacific coast; Vigilance committees -- California -- San Francisco; Mormons -- California; Indians of North America -- Religion -- 19th century; West (U.S.) -- Description and travel; California -- Religious life and customs; California -- Emigration and immigration; California -- Economic conditions; California -- Gold discoveries; California -- Description and travel; California -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; California -- History -- 1846-1850; Sacramento (Calif.) -- Description and travel; San Francisco (Calif.) -- Description and travel; San Francisco (Calif.) -- Politics and government; Panama -- Description and travel; Yuba County (Calif.) -- Politics and government; Nevada City (Calif.) -- Politics and government; Yosemite -- Description and travel; Pictorial lettersheets -- West (U.S.) -- 19th century; Miners -- California -- 19th century; Overland journeys to the Pacific -- 1851; Murphys (Calif.) -- Description and travel; Edmunds, A. C.; Edmunds, Cynthia; Field, Edward G.; Field, Henry B.; Fox, P. V., 1821-; Guthrie, James, active 1856; Hammond, John Henry, 1833-1890; Hyde, C. C.; Jones, George Warren; Kendall, George A.; Kerr, James, active 1850-1853; Kerr, Hetty Ann; Latimer, L. D.; Leibee, Daniel; Lewis, Joseph E.; Lippincott, Benjamin S.; Lott, Charles F.; McDougall, Walter; McRay, Thomas; Marcy, William L. (William Learned), 1786-1857; Mathews, L. M.; Merrow, William H.; Morris, William P., active 1849; Morrison, John H.; Pond, Benjamin Franklin; Scranton, Joel G.; Shumway, S. A.; Southwick, Benjamin, active 1851-1863; Southwick, Lawson; Smith, H. A. P.; Smith, James J., active 1850; Stanley, Benjamin Moors; Steele, William, active 1849; Thorndike, A.; Wetmore, E.; Baird, Samuel, active 1849; Haight, Henry H., 1825-1878; Bullock, J. J.; Colburn, Adeline N.; Gregory, D. S., active 1852; McElroy, R. M.; McHenry, John, 1809-1880; McLellan, Josiah; Parker, Manuel; Vincent, Achmet
- Edmunds, A. C. and Cynthia, 1852-1860 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Autograph letters, signed, from A. C. Edmunds from Downieville, California to his family in Michigan concerning his life in California, the Universalist faith, his work as a missionary preacher to Gold Rush miners, and the temperance movement. With three letters to Cynthia Edmunds from unidentified friends, a poem entitled "My Sister's Grave," and unidentified manuscript poems and speeches.
- Field, Edward G., 1852-1854 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Autograph letters, signed, from Sacramento, California, to Field's sister, commenting on raising hogs during the Gold Rush and the high level of immigration to California.
- Field, Henry B., 1850 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Autograph letters, signed, from San Francisco to a "Mr. Merriman." The letters concern Field's efforts to sell newspapers, become a merchant, and work as a miner. Field gives lengthy descriptions of the process of mining and the life of miners.
- Fox, Peren V., 1853-1855 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Autograph letters, signed, from Mariposa, California to Fox's wife Ida, and a letter to Fox from an E. Leland regarding Leland's employment.
- Hammond, John Henry, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Typescript copy of a letter from San Francisco to "Mr. and Mrs. Henry Conklin" regarding Hammond's journey to California, especially his travels through Yosemite.
- Hyde, C. C., 1851 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Autograph letters, signed, from San Francisco concerning Hyde's financial and legal struggles, including his efforts to obtain money he is owed by selling Los Angeles gold stock.
- Jones, George Warren, 1859-1861 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Seventeen autograph letters, signed, to Jones' father from a steamship, Crescent City, California, and Smith River Valley, California. Letters concern mining, lumber, an 1860 massacre at Carson Valley of white people by Native Americans, and Indian rain dances.
- Kendall, George A., [1850?] April 10 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
  Autograph letter, signed, to his brother-in-law, Benjamin Moors Stanley, describing his life as a miner in Diamond Springs, California, particularly his mining work and social interactions.
- Kerr family, 1850-1853 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Autograph letters, signed, to James and Hetty Ann Kerr from members of the Kerr-Johnston family. Letters describe the Gold Rush, Fort Laramie, Fort Kearney, crossing the plains to California, and mining life.
- Latimer, L. D., 1877 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Autograph statement, signed, by Latimer as U.S. Attorney, District of California, San Francisco, that no indictment has been found against any persons for collecting the Foreign Miners License Tax.
- Leibee, Daniel, 1850-1866 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Autograph letters, signed, from Peru and Sacramento, Sonora, and San Francisco, California to Leibee's wife and other family members describing mining and life in California, his fellow miners, moving to Peru to mine, religious matters, and the American Civil War.
- Lewis, Joseph E., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Autograph letter, signed, to Lewis from an unidentified writer from San Francisco regarding a book order and mining.
- Lippincott, Benjamin S., 1849 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Autograph letter, signed, from Stockton regarding a local precinct election, with a small sketch of the San Joaquin River and a report of a journey passing the river.
- Lott, Charles F., 1854-1882 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Autograph letters, signed, from the Steamer Panama, a letter to Lott from an unidentified friend, a 1867 circular on mining claims, a land indenture on Feather River, and an IOU.
- McDougall, Walter, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Autograph letter, signed, from New York regarding establishing a household in San Francisco and obtaining enough capital to do so.
- McRay, Thomas, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Autograph letter, signed, from San Francisco to a friend about life in California.
- Marcy, William L., 1849 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Autograph letter, signed, from Marcy, U.S. Secretary of War, from Washington, D.C. regarding reports of gold in California.
- Mathews, L. M., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Autograph letter, signed, from Marysville, California to "Maggie" on economic conditions, getting his photograph taken in a "Photographie Saloon," and attempting to convince "Maggie" to come to California.
- Merrow, William H., 1851 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Autograph letter, signed, to Merrow's sister regarding his life in California and the vigilance movement in San Francisco.
- Morris, William P., 1849 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Autograph letter, signed, from Bristol, Rhode Island to William Bonney, a sailor, regarding gold mania.
- Morrison, John H., 1849-1850 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Autograph letters, signed, from Rio de Janeiro and San Francisco to Morrison's family regarding his stay in Rio de Janeiro and his voyage to California via Cape Horn, as well as the population explosion and high cost of living in San Francisco.
- The People of Nevada City to the County Court of Yuba County, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Autograph petition to establish a police force, written in an unidentified hand and signed by eleven men.
- Pond, Benjamin Franklin, 1847-1853 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Autograph letters, signed, from San Francisco and Greenwood Ranch, California to Pond's parents regarding mob law, violence, and vigilance committees during the Gold Rush, as well as family matters and expenses.
- Scranton, Joel G., 1852 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Autograph letters, signed, from Sacramento to Scranton's brother regarding gold, crops, "yellow boys," and a flood.
- Shumway, S. A., 1853-1854 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Autograph letters, signed, from Georgetown, California concerning Shumway's work in the gold mines.
- Southwick, Benjamin and Lawson, 1851-1863 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Autograph letters, signed, from Sacramento regarding the brothers' business supplying goods to miners, including milk, and Lawson's 1852 death by bilious colic or cholera.
- Smith, H. P. A., 1856-03-19 (Box 1, Folder 25a)
  Autograph letter, signed, to James Guthrie, Secretary of the Treasury, Custom House, San Francisco, regarding Smith's work and pay as a clerk in the Custom House
- Smith, James J., 1850 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Autograph letter, signed, from San Francisco about the lumber trade and commerce.
- Steele, William, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Autograph letter, signed, from Sacramento about trying to make his fortune in gold mining.
- Thorndike, A., 1851 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Autograph letter, signed, from San Francisco to a "Captain I. Snow" about Thorndike's passage to California and arrival in San Francisco.
- Wetmore, E., 1849 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Autograph letter, signed, from Benicia, California requesting to send $250 home in gold dust.
- Unidentified, 1849-1850 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Letters from unidentified authors from San Francisco, Panama, New York, and Peoria on a variety of subjects, including mining, a voyage through Panama from New York to San Francisco, a description of the city of San Francisco, and Mormons. Also includes a letter on Levi pictorial letterhead advertising denim pants to miners.